Guide to the Cronly Family Papers, 1806-1944
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Cronly Family papers 1806-1944
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Cronly family
28 linear feet Extent: 1,962 Items
The Cronly family included Michael Cronly, Sr., auctioneer and real estate broker of Wilmington, N.C. and his wife, Margaret McLaurin Cronly and their nine children. Collection includes correspondence, legal papers, finanical papers, writings, account books, volumes, clippings and printed material. It ranges in date from 1806-1944.
RL.00272
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Cronly Family Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift and purchase between 1968-1969.
Biographical Note
The Cronly family of Wilmington, N.C. includes Michael Cronly, Sr., auctioneer and real estate broker, and his wife, Margaret McLaurin Cronly as well as their nine children.
Collection Overview
Correspondence, financial records, legal and other papers of the Cronly family. Subjects include auctions and auctioneering, Wilmington social life, Civil War experiences, the Wilmington, Charlotte and Rutherford Railway Company, railroad bonds issued in North Carolina during Reconstruction, an earthquake that struck the Carolinas in 1886, the Democratic Party and politics in North Carolina, and blacks during Reconstruction. Includes information on the Beatty, McLaurin and Murphy families of North Carolina, and descriptions of Charleston, Atlantic City (N.J.), Denver, Genoa (Italy), and the Hudson Fulton Celebration in New York City (1909). Correspondents include Thomas Walter Bickett, Jr., Harley Lyman Clarke, Stephen William Cole, Newton Martin Curtis, William Darius Jamieson, Herbert Putnam, Don Carlos Seitz, William Nathan Harrell Smith, Waddy Thompson, and Platt Dickinson Walker. The collection ranges in date from 1806-1944.
Collection also contains numerous bound volumes, ledgers, and account books that have not been inventoried or described.
Subject Headings
Beatty family; Bickett, Thomas Walter, 1869-1921; Clarke, Harley Lyman; Cole, Stephen William; Cronly family; Cronly, Margaret McLaurin, d. 1891; Cronly, Michael, Sr; Curtis, Newton Martin, 1835-1910; Jamieson, William Darius; McLaurin family; Murphy family; Seitz, Don Carlos, 1862-1935; Smith, William N. H. (William Nathan Harrell), 1812-1889; Thompson, Waddy; Walker, Platt Dickinson; Democratic Party (N.C.); Wilmington, Charlotte, and Rutherford Railway Company; Freedmen -- North Carolina; Hudson-Fulton Celebration, 1909; Railroads -- North Carolina; Reconstruction (U.S. history, 1865-1877) -- North Carolina; Earthquakes -- Southern states; Auctioneers -- North Carolina; Real estate agents -- North Carolina; North Carolina -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Personal narratives, Confederate; Wilmington (N.C.) -- Social life and customs; Family life -- North Carolina -- United States
Contents of Collection
- Genealogy
  - Genealogical information (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1816-1944, undated
  - 1816-1873 (Box 1)
  - 1874-1897 (Box 2)
  - 1898-1915 (Box 3)
  - 1916-1944, undated (Box 4)
- Legal Papers, 1806-1931, undated
  - 1806-1885 (Box 4)
  - 1886-1931, undated (Box 5)
- Financial Papers, 1806-1942, undated
  - 1806-1942, undated (Box 5)
  - Tax Lists (Box 6)
- Miscellaneous
  - Clippings and Printed Material (Box 6)
- Writings
  - (Box 7-8)
- Letter Book, 1824-1826
  - 1824-1826 (Box 9)
- Letterpress Books, 1868-1885
  - 1868-1878 (Box 9)
  - 1879-1881 Aug. 23 (Box 10)
  - 1881 Aug. 24-1883 Oct 18 (Box 11)
  - 1883 Oct. 19-1885 (Box 12)
  - Unidentified letterpress books (Box 22)
- Account Books, 1837-1892
  - 1837-1879 (Box 13)
  - 1870-1874 (Box 14)
  - 1871-1884 (Box 15)
  - 1873-1876 (Box 16)
  - 1876-1879 (Box 17)
  - 1878-1891 (Box 18)
  - 1882-1891 (Box 19)
  - 1886-1892 (Box 20)
  - 1889-1892, Miscellaneous vols. (race riot account) (Box 21)
- Bound Volumes
  Ledgers, account books, and other bound volumes relating chiefly to the business interests of the Cronly family. Volumes have not been individually identified or described.
  - Unidentified bound volumes (Volume 1-27)
- Photographs
  - Various photographs (Box 21)